NYSUT Division of Research and Educational Services Files. 6174/003
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
- Certification – Susan Cramer, 1993 (Box 71, Folder 4)
  Correspondence and documentation re hardship case in request for extension for obtaining master's degree
- George Jr. Republic – Certification, 1991 (Box 71, Folder 5)
  Correspondence between NYSUT associate and State Education Department re requirements for certification in special education at a school in Freeville with 99 percent emotionally disturbed students
- Certification – Dominick Iacovazzi, 1991 (Box 71, Folder 6)
  Correspondence from teacher and his supervisor at Union Endicott School District seeking resolution of master's degree requirement for permanent certification in earth science
- Certification – Cassidy Request, 1991 (Box 71, Folder 7)
  October 18, 1991. Correspondence re certification of a special education teacher in Greenburgh Eleven Union Free School District
- Certification Issues – Onondaga Count, 1991 (Box 71, Folder 8)
  Correspondence re classification of certain job titles
- Certification – Roder Gustavson (Yorktown), 1990 (Box 71, Folder 9)
  Correspondence between Yorktown Congress of Teachers and NYSUT Vice President Antonia Cortese over forced part-time status of teacher affecting retirement pension
- Certification – Leslie Roraback, 1989 (Box 71, Folder 10)
  Correspondence re teacher in East Syracuse
- Certification – Lynn Sandberg, 1990 (Box 71, Folder 11)
  Correspondence re special education master's degree requirements for teacher in Brooklyn
- Certification – Miscellaneous, 1987 (Box 71, Folder 12)
- TC II (FF) – Psychology, 1987 (Box 71, Folder 13)
  Commissioner's Regulations, with cover note re endorsement by NYS Psychological Association
- TC II (GG) – Occupational Therapy, 1987 (Box 71, Folder 14)
  Commissioner's Regulations; copy of Assembly bill
- ACSA Survey on Employment of Non-Counselors, 1991 (Box 71, Folder 15)
  American School Counselors Association report
- Wappingers Falls – Pisarek v. Wappingers Falls, 1988-1991 (Box 71, Folder 16)
  Chronological listing of file contents/actions in the case re use of non-certified drug and alcohol counselors; correspondence; legal exhibits; decision
- Wappingers Falls – Louise Tricard, 1988-1989 (Box 71, Folder 17)
- TC II (ii) – Guidance Counselors, 1991 (Box 71, Folder 18)
  Letter from NYS School Counselor Association to NYSUT Vice President Antonia Cortese re use of non-certified counselors
- Certification – Gary Wohl, 1988-1991 (Box 71, Folder 19)
  Correspondence re English as a Second Language certification amnesty for NYC teacher
- Principal Teacher Resolution (Miller), 1991 (Box 71, Folder 20)
  December, 1991. Correspondence re proposed resolution supporting tenure for principals and removing the separation between administrators and classroom teachers; discussion document
- TC II (k) Alternative Certification – New Jersey Plan, 1985-1990 (Box 71, Folder 21)
  Correspondence from Texas Education Association and NYSUT re certifying teachers at the district level; article in Phi Delta Kappan discussing New Jersey Plan, June 1985
- TC II (kk) – Alternative Schools, 1989 (Box 71, Folder 22)
  Report, Alternative Teacher Certification in Texas; U.S Department of Education information paper, "The Educational Excellence Act of 1989"; Los Angeles United School District Personnel Division report, District Intern Program, 1984-1989; letter to NYSUT from State Education Department
- Early Childhood Advisory Committee, 1988-1990 (Box 71, Folder 23)
  Report to the Governor and Legislature by the Task Force on Early Childhood Services, "Expanding Early Childhood Services in New York State," November 1988; article reprints; notice of meeting of Ad Hoc Early Childhood Advisory Committee, 2/28/90
- Task Force on Early Childhood Certification Requirements, 1989-1991 (Box 71, Folder 24)
  Discussion papers; correspondence
- TC II (LL) – Foreign Language Instruction, 1991 (Box 71, Folder 25)
  NYSUT memo re proposed amendment to Commissioner's Regulations
- Adult Education Certification, 1991-1994 (Box 71, Folder 26)
  Paper, "Certification for Adult Educators in New York State, or Going Through the Back Door When the Front Door Is Slammed," by Kathleen Graham Kelly, December 10, 1993; comments on paper from NYSUT associate Pat Flynn, January 17, 1994; related memo
- Adult Education – NYC/NYS Alliance for Adult Education/Training Proposal, 1991 (Box 71, Folder 27)
  May, 1991. Draft letter re proposed certification requirements for adult education teachers, March 1, 1991; discussion paper
- Adult Learning Services Council, 1991 (Box 71, Folder 28)
  Council meeting minutes, February 25-26, 1991; minutes of finance committee, February 25, 1991; memo
- Adult Education – Commissioner's Regulation, 1988-1989 (Box 71, Folder 29)
  Correspondence; copy of regulations
- Adult Education – Report from NYSUT Representative, 1990 (Box 71, Folder 30)
  Adult Learning Services Council minutes, February 6-7, 1990, with cover letter from Albany school district superintendent
- Certification Requirements for Teachers of Adult, Community, and Continuing Education, 1990-1991 (Box 71, Folder 31)
  Correspondence, draft regulations, and discussion papers re bilingual, early childhood, and adult education certification
- TC II (BB) – Substitute Teachers, 1988 (Box 71, Folder 32)
  Proposed NYSUT policy; memo
- TC II (CC) Dance Certification, 1990 (Box 71, Folder 33)
  Fact sheet; memo re proposed NYSUT policy
- Outside Substance Abuse Programs – Local Presidents' Survey, 1991 (Box 71, Folder 34)
  Survey and cover memo
- TC II (DD) – Health Education, 1987-1988 (Box 71, Folder 35)
  Memo re court decision in case of Catherine Maloney; decision by State Education Department denying appeal by Joan Mead; copy of provisional certificate of Joseph Henry Gilbo; copy of Commissioner's Regulations; related correspondence
- Certification – Diane Zansitis, 1991 (Box 71, Folder 36)
  Correspondence requesting extension of certification deadline for medical reasons
- TC II (EE) – Teachers with Health Related Problems, 1987 (Box 71, Folder 37)
  Newspaper clippings re Supreme Court decision on dismissal of workers with contagious diseases
- TAAP (Teaching as a Profession) See also: Regents Regional Conference See also: Task Force on the Teaching Profession, 1985 (Box 71, Folder 38)
  Text of Assembly bill to amend education law to require licensing as a profession, March 5, 1985; memos to and from NYSUT research director Santelli analyzing bill, noting very few benefits for teachers and many liabilities; testimony by NYSUT president Thomas Hobart to Regents re Tentative Proposal on Teaching as a Profession and Teacher Competence, calling document "explosive," April 11, 1980; handwritten notes
- Teaching as a Profession/Competency, 1980-1981 (Box 71, Folder 39)
  December, 19. Memo from Education Commissioner Gordon Ambach to members of the Teacher Education, Certification and Practice Board re issues raised for consideration by Regents, October 1, 1980; testimony by NYSUT Vice President Antonia Cortese to Regents re proposed regulations on teaching as a profession/teacher competence, February 25, 1981; text of draft regulations
- Teaching as a Profession – Public Hearings, 1980 (Box 71, Folder 40)
  Letters from State Education Department confirming speakers at hearing; handwritten notes
- Teacher Centers, 1984 (Box 71, Folder 41)
  Correspondence re Teacher Resource and Computer Training Centers
- Teacher Education, Certification and Practice Board (TECAP) See also: Certification See also: National Association of State Directors Teacher Education and Certification See also: Task Force on the Teaching Profession, 1985 (Box 71, Folder 42)
  Letter to Education Commissioner Gordon Ambach from Patricia M. Kay, chair of Teacher Education, Certification and Practice Board, recommending regulatory or legislative changes, November 8, 1985; article by Kay, "Some Thoughts on a Possible TECAP Recommendation about Computers and Teacher Education/Certification," January 1985; article by Kay, "Toward the Statewide Identification of Minimal Essential Computer Competencies: Analysis of New York State Responses," NCSIE Annual Meeting, November 1984
- Teacher Education, Certification and Practice Board (TECAP), 1992-1993 (Box 71, Folder 43)
  Meeting minutes; policy memos; description of NYSUT Effective Teaching Program
- TECAP (Teacher Education, Certification and Practice Board) Nominations, 1977-1984 (Box 71, Folder 44)
  NYSUT letter nominating Nettie Webb and Betty Holms to teacher vacancies on TECAP board, 1984; letter nominating George Stevens, 1977; resumes.
- TECAP Board Meeting, 1989 (Box 71, Folder 45)
  May 10-11, 1989. Proposed Part 81 of Commissioner's Regulations re teacher resource and computer training centers; minutes
- TECAP Subcommittee Meeting, 1984 (Box 71, Folder 46)
  September 13, 1984. Memos re teacher resource and training centers, with staff rating summary, May 18, 1984; local assessment of NYSUT services, with draft survey for comment, September 12
- TECAP, 1984 (Box 71, Folder 47)
  April, 1984. Minutes of meeting, February 28-March 1, 1983, and March 22-23, 1984; State Education Department procedures and criteria for evaluation of language skills of applicants for certification of teachers of bilingual education and English to speakers of other languages; text of relevant Commissioner's Regulations; bylaws, 1982
- TECAP, 1984-1987 (Box 71, Folder 48)
  Summary of meeting with Commissioner Sobol, October 19-20, 1987; related correspondence, including transcript; urgent memo re Commissioner's "shameless misuse" of TECAP, January 14, 1985; TECAP by-laws
- TECAP – Good Moral Character, 1978-1987 (Box 71, Folder 49)
  Summary of meeting, including discussion re background checks and fingerprinting, February 26-17, 1987; excerpts from Commissioner's regulations re good moral character, creation of TECAP; by-laws; letter to Commissioner Ambach from TECAP chair recommending change to good moral character provision re location of hearings, April 13, 1978
- Teacher Education Conference Board (TECB), 1983 (Box 71, Folder 50)
  Letters of regret from Albert Shanker and others at inability to attend dinner for Thomas Hobart and Daniel Griffiths on their retirement from board
- Teacher Education Conference Board (TECB), 1977-1984 (Box 72, Folder 1)
  Constitution of TECAP; description of organizational objectives; letter describing impetus for creation of TECB, March 30, 1977; State Education Department memo re proposed content of "Federal Legislation and Education in New York State, 1984," September 26, 1983, with cover letter to TECB, October 5; position paper, "The Effective Teacher," second draft, November 1980; position paper, "Morality in the Classroom: Establishing a Climate for the Development of Ethical Behavior," July 1981; paper, "Developing Computer Literacy and Competency for Preservice and Inservice Teachers," (no date).; memo, Interview with Dr. Vince Gazzetta, November 14, 1981; agenda for December 11, 1981, meeting; minutes of September 25, 1981, meeting; treasurer's report, December 11, 1981; list of organizations on mailing list; correspondence re paper, "The Effective Teacher," 1981
- TECB – Requests for Position Papers, 1984-1985 (Box 72, Folder 2)
  Requests for "Teaching as a Profession," "The Effective Teacher," and "Teaching and Leaning with Computers"
- TECB Invoices, 1981-1984 (Box 72, Folder 3)
  Invoices for "Teaching and Learning with Computers" brochures, other publications and items
- TECB/Regents, 1981 (Box 72, Folder 4)
  Regents meeting minutes and correspondence
- Teacher Evaluation (folder 1), 1984-1991 (Box 72, Folder 5)
  NYSUT correspondence; scholarly article reprints
- Teacher Evaluation (folder 2), 1973-1983 (Box 72, Folder 6)
  Correspondence; reports
- Teacher Evaluation (Fredonia), 1986 (Box 72, Folder 7)
  Fredonia Central School District Annual Professional Performance Review: Teacher Evaluation, July 9, 1985; description of Fredonia Teachers' Association Mentor Program
- Teacher-to-Teacher Conference Niagara Frontier, 1979 (Box 72, Folder 8)
  March 17, 1979. NYSUT publication with charts and graphs, "Analysis of State Aid," March 1979; fact sheet, "Individual School District Comparisons under Gov. Carey's 1979-80 Operating Aid Proposal (part of 1979-80 Executive Budget Proposals on State Aid to Public Schools)"; outline of topics for meeting, NYSUT Commission on Equitable Funding, March 2-3; handwritten notes
- Teacher-to-Teacher Conference Central NYS, 1977 (Box 72, Folder 9)
  October 15, 1977. Regents Proposal to Change the School Calendar; agenda for Fourth Annual Central New York Teacher-to-Teacher Conference; handwritten notes
- Teacher-to-Teacher Conference Regional Education Conferences, 1975-1976 (Box 72, Folder 10)
  Memo announcing conference
- Albany Regional Educational Conference, 1975 (Box 72, Folder 11)
  May 3, 1975. Data on finances and registration
- Teacher-to-Teacher Conference Rochester, 1975 (Box 72, Folder 12)
  February 8, 1975. NYSUT press release, "Albert Shanker and Russell Baker to Keynote Rochester Regional Educational Conference"; conference program
- Teacher-to-Teacher Conference Long Island, 1974 (Box 72, Folder 13)
  October 26, 1974. Memo announcing conference
- Teacher-to-Teacher Conference Southern Tier, 1975 (Box 72, Folder 14)
  March 1, 1975. Conference program
- Teacher-to-Teacher Conferences, 1974-1975 (Box 72, Folder 15)
  Committee on Committees Report, September 13, 1974; background paper on NYSUT regional educational conferences
- Teacher-to-Teacher Conference Days (folder 1), 1976-1980 (Box 72, Folder 16)
  List of conference chairpersons; handbook for designing a teacher-to-teacher conference; program for Lower Hudson Valley Regional Conference, November 13, 1976; minutes of steering committee, June 3, 1976; financial statements; related correspondence
- Teacher-to-Teacher Conference Days (folder 2), 1974-1976 (Box 72, Folder 17)
  Announcement of conference days; correspondence re various regional conferences
- Teacher to Teacher Conference, 1981 (Box 72, Folder 18)
  March 27, 1981. Memos expressing concern over costs of conferences; overview report on conferences 1980-81; list of topics for April 11, 1981, conference in Syracuse
- Teacher to Teacher Chairperson Meeting, 1982 (Box 72, Folder 19)
  May 26, 1982. Agenda; handbook for designing teach-to-teacher conferences
- Teacher to Teacher Conference – Tri-County, 1981 (Box 72, Folder 20)
  October 17, 1981. Invitation to Santelli, with description of program
- Teaching and America's Future, National Commission, 1996 (Box 72, Folder 21)
  Text of report
- Technology See also: Regents Advisory Council for Learning Technologies
- Technology Issues, 1997-1998 (Box 72, Folder 22)
  Meeting memos; agenda for Library Task Force meeting, July 14, 1997
- Teenage Pregnancy Conferences, 1985 (Box 72, Folder 23)
  Grant proposal; correspondence
- Tenure – Valley Stream, 1996-1997 (Box 72, Folder 24)
  Correspondence re tenure for vocational teachers and generally; remarks by United Liverpool (NY) Faculty Association president to Renewable Tenure Forum, Syracuse, October 8, 1996
- Think Technologies, Inc. See also: Effective Teaching Program (ETP) Regional Coordinators Meeting, 1984 (Box 72, Folder 25)
  Letters to NYSUT research director Charles Santelli and Blind Brook-Rye school superintendent from Think, outlining terms to provide computer support for Effective Teaching Program.
- Tonawanda, 1985 (Box 72, Folder 26)
  Handwritten notes of telephone conversations
- Truth in Testing, 1977-1988 (Box 72, Folder 27)
  Testimony before the Subcommittee on Elementary, Secondary and Vocational Education of the Committee on Education and Labor, House of Representatives, by Albert Shanker, President, American Federation of Teachers, AFL-CIO, October 11, 1979; proceedings of the National Conference on Testing: Major Issues, Center for Advanced Study in Education (CASE), Graduate School and University Center of the City University of New York, 1977; "Public Interest Principles for the Design and Use of Admissions Testing Programs," proposed for discussion by the College Board, Educational Testing Service, Graduate Management Admission Council, Graduate Record Examinations Board, and Law School Admission Council; text of proposed legislation in New York and California; NYSUT memos analyzing bills; letter to Albert Shanker from College Board re proposed NY legislation, May 20, 1988
- Tuition Tax Credits – Reports (folder 1), 1937-1980 (Box 72, Folder 28)
  Booklet, "Public Education in New York State: A Brief Outline of the History, Development and Organization of State Public School System and a Digest of the Laws Under Which It Operates," New York State Teachers Association, 1937; book, "Education in New York State, 1784-1954," by the NY State Education Department, 1954; Congressional Quarterly article, "House Rejects Effort to Prevent Floor Vote on Tuition Tax Credit," March 25, 1978; article from Education USA, "Tax Credits Would Aid Affluent," August 18, 1980; newspaper clippings
- Tuition Tax Credits – Reports (folder 2), 1981-1982 (Box 73, Folder 1)
  Regents Task Force on Tuition Tax Credits Background Materials: Preliminary Report, December 7, 1982; Working Papers in Educational Policy, No. 1: "Tuition Tax Relief: Aid for Non-Public Schools Revisited," Center for Educational Research and Policy Studies, June 1981; "Selected Articles on Tuition Tax Credits, Pro and Con," (no date)., including articles by Albert Shanker, Sen. Daniel Patrick Moynihan, Sen. Ernest Hollings, Bayard Rustin, Gus Tyler; text of Senate bill (S. 550) to provide a federal tuition tax credit, February 1981; NYSUT Information Bulletins: "Tuition Tax Credits for Nonpublic Schools," March 1981; "Trends in Enrollment, Staff and Schoolhousing in Public and Nonpublic Elementary and Secondary Schools – The Implications Relating to Tuition Tax Credits," March 1981; "Potential Impact of Tuition Tax Credits on Public Support of Public Schools School Budget Votes," March 1981; "Tuition Tax Credits: Public Funds for Nonpublic Schools," March 1981; "Who Will Benefit From Tuition Tax Credits?" March 1981
- Tuition Tax Credits – Religious Schools (folder 3), 1981-1982 (Box 73, Folder 2)
  Materials by Pensacola Christian College book publisher Beka Book Publications; report to the National Center for Educational Statistics by National Opinion Research Center, "Summary of Major Findings for Public and Private Schools," March 1981; discussion paper distributed by the Council for Educational Development and Research, "Irrelevant Social Facts? A Brief Critique of the Usefulness of the 'Private and Public Schools' Report for the Tuition Tax Debate," prepared by James M. McPartland, Center for Social Organization of Schools, Johns Hopkins University, April 6, 1981; clippings; correspondence
- Tuition Tax Credits (folder 4), 1983-1985 (Box 73, Folder 3)
  Booklet by New York State Educational Conference Board, "A Primer on Tuition Tax Credits," with attached cover letter from NYSUT Vice President Antonia Cortese recommending it to Board of Directors, June 7, 1983; NYSUT special order resolution opposing tuition tax credits, April 1985; New York State School Boards Association legislative memo and bulletin opposing tuition tax credits, May 1985; NYSUT fact sheet: "Some Facts regarding Tax Benefits to Parents of Nonpublic School Students in New York State," April 1985; testimony before New York State Senate Committee on Education hearing on Funding of Elementary and Secondary Education, presented by Joan Ball, chairman, Coalition for Public Education, February 10, 1984; policy perspective papers by Institute for Research on Educational Finance and Government (IGF), winter 1982; outline of reasons for opposing tuition tax credits, by NYS Council of School District Administrators, October 6, 1981; draft of "Public Schools Are for All America: A Primer on Tuition Tax Credits"; comments on draft; clippings
- Tuition Tax Credit – Moynihan/Packwood Bill, 1981 (Box 73, Folder 4)
  Memos and packets for lobbying campaign against bill, including article reprints, call sheets listing congressional aides; related materials
- Tuition Tax Credits, 1984-1986 (Box 73, Folder 5)
  List of members of Tuition Tax Credit Task Force; letters from Republican state senators Frank Padavan and Michael Tully in response to letter re tuition tax credit legislation, with cover letter from Great Neck Teachers Association to NYSUT vice president Antonia Cortese, April 30, 1985; resolution by NYSUT opposing tuition tax credits; statement by Albert Shanker, president, United Federation of Teachers and American Federation of Teachers, before a legislative hearing of the NYS Senate Standing Committee on Education, February 10, 1984; paper, "Teaching Values in Public Schools: Can It Be Done Adequately within Our Present System?" by Richard A. Baer, Jr., College of Agriculture and Life Sciences, Cornell University; NYSUT tuition tax credit kit of materials; NYS School Boards Association Federal Legislative Bulletin, re tax voucher bill, November 22, 1985; description of the Equity and Choice Act of 1985 (TEACH); letter to State Education Department from Smithtown Christian School re whether PEP Test in Social Studies would be mandated for non-public schools, noting different teaching by school re evolution and other topics, December 16, 1986; newspaper clippings and journal articles
- Tuition Tax Credit Campaign, 1985 (Box 73, Folder 6)
  Brochure, "Tuition Tax Credits: Writing to Your Legislators Is Not a Waste of Time!" and related flyers; NYSUT memo, Cost of Senator Marchi Tuition Tax Credit Bill, April 16, 1985; unsigned speech for NEA of New York, March 18, 1985; related materials
- Tuition Tax Credits – Coalition for Public Education, 1985-1986 (Box 73, Folder 7)
  Materials against using public funds for non-public schools
- Tuition Tax Credits (State), 1985 (Box 73, Folder 8)
  Correspondence; memos by several groups in opposition to proposed legislation by state senator John Marchi
- Unemployment, 1977-1982 (Box 73, Folder 9)
  NYS Department of Labor report, "Local Governments Coverage under the NYS Unemployment Insurance" (reprinted by NYSUT), September 1977; monthly legislative report by Public Employee Department, AFL-CIO, September 1977; magazine clipping
- Urban Coalition, 1981 (Box 73, Folder 10)
  Minutes of December 8, 1981 meeting, summary of Appellate Division's Decision in Levittown v. Nyquist, October 30, 1981; spreadsheet of aid formula simulations; memo to members of NYS Special Task Force on Equity and Excellence in Education; printed booklet, "Security in the Schools"; handwritten notes
- Values and Student Conduct, 1981 (Box 73, Folder 11)
  Article reprints; handwritten notes; list of topics for NYSUT values project; discussion paper by State Education Department; text of speech by Mark Cannon, administrative assistant to the Chief Justice of the United States, "Crime and the Decline of Values"
- Vocational Education See: Occupational Education See: BOCES
- World Congress of Education See: International – Education International World Congress
- World of Difference Campaign to Reduce Prejudice, 1987 (Box 73, Folder 12)
  Letters to NYSUT Vice President Antonia Cortese from Jane Golub (Golub Corporation), coordinator of Albany/Schenectady-area "A World of Difference" awareness-raising project, sponsored by the Anti-Defamation League of B'nai B'rith, Price Chopper Supermarkets, and WTEN-TV; handwritten notes
- Youth Together for Tomorrow, 1974 (Box 73, Folder 13)
  Proposal for satellite school project, (no date).; NYSUT memo describing YTT, September 10, 1974